Finding Aid for Department of Screen Arts and Cultures (University of Michigan) records, 1988-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Screen Arts and Cultures (University of Michigan) records 1988-2005, 1995-1999
University of Michigan. Department of Screen Arts and Cultures.
1 linear foot
2008152 Bimu 2
The Department of Screen Arts and Cultures at the University of Michigan began in 1972 as an interdisciplinary concentration eventually called the Program in Film and Video Studies. The program brought together the film classes taught by different university departments into a viable concentration for students interested in film. The record group mainly encompasses the administrative activities of the department from 1988 to 2005. Records include: administrative papers and correspondence, program reviews, curriculum requirements, and funding matters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the Department of Screen Arts and Cultures (Donor number 10,102 ) were received in August 2008.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction
Before the establishment of the Program in Film and Video Studies, courses dealing with film, television, and video were spread out across different university departments. The English, Communications, American Culture and Art History departments each offered film classes. Each developed courses as the subject of film pertained to their discipline and no centralized major existed that focused on film studies. In 1972, several faculty and staff members recognized the need for the centralization of film studies. They hoped to establish a liberal arts concentration recognizing the ever growing discipline of film as an academic subject. The Program in Film and Video Studies was developed as an undergraduate program to train students in the history, theory, and analysis of film, with an emphasis on liberal arts as opposed to production.
According to the 1988 program review, the program initially was housed in one room of Lorch Hall and a part-time director was assigned, who did not receive any additional compensation for the role. (Given the informal nature of the early program the name of said director could not be positively determined). A part time administrative assistant also was hired to assist the director and counsel students. The program drew on faculty from different departments to teach its classes. Early on, the program was simply an interdisciplinary concentration and received little recognition. In the summer of 1976, the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (LSA) approved it as one of their undergraduate programs giving it cohesion and focus. It also marked the first independent course taught by the program.
The curriculum initially offered two classes in film and video. By the end of the 1970s, ten additional classes had been added to the concentration to bring the total classes offered to twelve. By 1987, the program had shown significant growth in its initial sixteen years and in 1988, a formal review of the program was undertaken. The review was intended to raise university awareness of the program, its growth, and its importance. The faculty and staff hoped the review would establish the Program in Film and Video Studies as an autonomous unit able to make its own decisions about faculty, curriculum, and budget. The review's report asked for the commitment of the university to establish the Program in Film and Video as an academic discipline. In doing so, the program gained a full time director, faculty, and administrative staff, as well as a yearly budget of $60,000 and some say in LSA decisions about equipment, technology, and faculty.
In 1993, a second program review was launched. The 1993 review looked at recommendations to improve and strengthen the program and interdisciplinary major. The review's report recommended the establishment of the program into a department outside the purview of the LSA so the program could focus on production courses as well as a liberal arts approach to film.
The program took a step towards autonomy in July 2001 when it received the ability to appoint faculty to tenured positions and to serve as a tenure home. In May 2005, the Board of Regents approved the establishment of the Program in Film and Video Studies as its own department to be called the Department of Screen Arts and Cultures
Department/Program Heads
Fall 1977 Diane Kirkpatrick
Spring 1978-Fall 1978 Alfredo Montalvo
Winter 1979-1980 Hubert Cohen
1981-1988 Herbert Eagle
1989-1990 Ira Koingsberg
1991-1992 William Paul
1992-1995 Ira Koingsberg
1995-2005 Gaylyn Studlar
2005- Richard Abel
The record group collectively deals with the operations of the Department of Screen Arts and Cultures, formerly known as the Program in Film and Video Studies, mostly during the period of time Gaylyn Studlar served as its director. The record group encompasses the years 1988-2005, but the majority of materials fall within the years 1995-1999. It includes four series: Administrative, Curriculum, Funding, and Publications.
Subjects:
Motion pictures--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Studlar, Gaylyn.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Screen Arts & Cultures.
- Administrative 1988-2003
  The Administrative Series (1988-2003) is arranged alphabetically and includes files dealing with program issues. It contains correspondence and e-mails (print outs) to and from Director Gaylyn Studlar dealing with equipment, space, and technology issues. A small file on notable alumni is included as well as some information of faculty and executive committees. Two program reviews, the first in 1988 and the second in 1993, important to the growth of the program, are also filed here. The reviews contain information regarding the history, development, faculty, curriculum, and critiques of the program.
  - Alumni (Box 1)
  - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (Box 1)
  - Director Gaylyn Studlar, Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Equipment Issues (Box 1)
  - Faculty and Executive Committee Meetings (Box 1)
  - Film Storage/Archival Issues (Box 1)
  - Media Union (Box 1)
  - Review Committee Report on the Program in Film and Video April 26, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Review of Film and Video Activities in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts June 1993 (Box 1)
  - Seeking Department Status (Box 1)
  - Space Issues (Box 1)
  - Technology Committee (Box 1)
- Curriculum 1992-2005
  The Curriculum Series (1992-2005) is arranged alphabetically and includes files pertaining to the development, establishment, and review of courses within the Program of Film and Video Studies. It includes some information on the bachelor and graduate programs, the honor's program, and internships, as well as a few miscellaneous syllabi. Some correspondence, the majority of it in e-mail format (print outs), is found here. A small file on guest lecturer Robert Wise, director of The Sound of Music and West Side Story is also included.
  - Bachelor Degree Revisions (Box 1)
  - Concentration in Dramatic Writing 1995-1997 (Box 1)
  - Concentration in Dramatic Writing 1999-2002 (Box 1)
  - Concentration in Dramatic Writing, Suspension of the (Box 1)
  - Course Overviews, Catalogs, Numberings, and Prerequisites (Box 1)
  - Film and Video 200 (Box 1)
  - Freshman Seminar (Box 1)
  - Graduate Program (Box 1)
  - Honor's Program Proposals (Box 1)
  - Internships (Box 1)
  - MFA in Media Arts (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Syllabi (Box 1)
  - Robert Wise Visit to Campus 1996-1997 (Box 1)
- Funding 1994-2004
  The Funding Series (1994-2004) is arranged alphabetically and contains files mostly dealing with the funding of the Program in Film and Video Studies. Individual donor files form the main body of this series but it also includes files on endowments.
  - Bob and Anne Smith, Donors (Box 1)
  - Bob Shaye, Donor 1995-2004, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Donors 1995-2002 (Box 1)
  - Endowment Background Research (1973-1996) circa 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Endowments 1995, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Four Friends Foundation, Donor (Box 1)
  - Gladys Nederlander, Donor (Box 1)
  - Henry, Melba, and Sidney Winer, Donors (Box 1)
  - Leonard and Eileen Newman, Donors (Box 1)
  - Peter Benedek, Donor (Box 1)
- Publications 1988-2005
  The Publications Series (1988-2005) contains program promotional pieces, brochures, newsletters, schedules of film showings, and a 2005 newsletter detailing the program's name change.
  - Newsletters, Brochures, and Campus Posters (Box 1)